<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>BuildingProductivity.tech - Productivity</title><link href="https://buildingproductivity.tech/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://buildingproductivity.tech/feeds/productivity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://buildingproductivity.tech/</id><updated>2020-06-03T12:30:00+10:00</updated><entry><title>Writing Well as a Project Manager</title><link href="https://buildingproductivity.tech/writing-well-as-a-project-manager.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-03T12:30:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T12:30:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Kim</name></author><id>tag:buildingproductivity.tech,2020-06-03:/writing-well-as-a-project-manager.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Improve your writing to get people to do stuff&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR: Use Grammarly and Hemmingway App. Be clear, set expectations and be respectful&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a project manager, I spend most of my time communicating in writing. I write many, many emails to consultants, contractors and internal staff. I write up reports for authorities sign off and write up minutes to meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At work, I write mostly to get people to do stuff.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to convince people to do stuff:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be clear on what you need them to do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set expectations and deadline if required&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be respectful&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to deter people from doing stuff&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a novel like the Ulysses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of action items or expectations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be rude and demanding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn't say I'm an excellent writer by any means, but here are some tips to help you write better and get people to do stuff without being their mum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use a Writing App&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use two &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt; app to write better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Grammarly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Grammarly Screenshot" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/grammarly.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grammarly&lt;/strong&gt; is a popular software which checks your spelling and grammar. You can get this as a browser extension and Outlook extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use this all the time. Although I cannot install the Outlook extension at work, I use the Chrome extension to write and check. I then copy it back to the body of the email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://app.grammarly.com/"&gt;Check out Grammarly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hemingway Editor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hemingway Editor Screenshot" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/hemingway-editor.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came upon this on a web development forum. &lt;strong&gt;Hemingway Editor&lt;/strong&gt; is an online app focuses on your writing style so that it is concise and readable. It checks your writing against "grade levels" required to understand your text. Your aim is to lower the "grade level". Their philosophy is that if Ernest Hemingway can write a book for adults with 5th grade literacy, then we should all be able to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note, it doesn't really check for spelling or grammar so use this in conjunction with Grammarly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hemingwayapp.com/"&gt;Check out Hemingway Editor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other helpful tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be clear&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know what you're writing about, don't pretend.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't understand completely, be clear about what you know and what you don't know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Break up sentences.&lt;/strong&gt;
  This helps to make ideas more digestible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce jargon as much as possible (especially in our industry!)&lt;/strong&gt;
  There are lots of acronyms in our industry such as RFT, RFI, PCDMA, LOA, etc. Try to use the full word unless it's used often. For example, I would use RFI in abbreviated form but not Letter of Award / Acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you have finished writing, read out loud what you have written&lt;/strong&gt;
  If it sounds unnatural, then it probably could be worded better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use bullet points&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Set Expectations and Deadlines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't beat around the bush.&lt;/strong&gt;
  It's awkward to ask people to do things. But just say it! (But nicely)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a list of action points&lt;/strong&gt;
  Who, what and by when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine whether you need to set deadlines&lt;/strong&gt;
  But you don't want to be setting deadlines all the time to people unless you want to perceive yourself as a micro manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be respectful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduce yourself if you haven't met them before&lt;/strong&gt;
  Could be simple as "Hi &lt;em&gt;(insert name)&lt;/em&gt;, My name is Andrew and I'm a project manager at &lt;em&gt;(insert company)&lt;/em&gt;. Nice to meet you".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine whether to "ask" or "command".&lt;/strong&gt;
  Whenever I need to get someone to do stuff, I would say &lt;em&gt;"could you do x,y,z"&lt;/em&gt;. When I need to come slightly harder on them, I would then say &lt;em&gt;"Please do x,y,z"&lt;/em&gt;. But I put the magic word in (please) so it's all good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask for their opinion&lt;/strong&gt;
  I usually end with "Let me know what you think" . Or, if I am proposing something, I say "Feel free to amend" so that they can voice their opinion (if they have any).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write better so that you can get people to do stuff, and be productive!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="communication"></category></entry><entry><title>Simplify the Management of Complex Passwords</title><link href="https://buildingproductivity.tech/simplify-the-management-of-complex-passwords.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-26T12:30:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-05-26T12:30:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Kim</name></author><id>tag:buildingproductivity.tech,2020-05-26:/simplify-the-management-of-complex-passwords.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why and how you should use a password manager.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDLR: Learn how to use a password manager.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our online life is complicated. For every online service out there, we need an account and a password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're working in the building sector like me, you would at least have a login for your laptop, Microsoft Exchange account, Aconex or Procore, Dropbox, Google Account, Apple Account... etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, things are sort of looking up. Logins are becoming simplified through social logins (connect to your Google Account or Microsoft Exchange Account). But not everything can or should be connected this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A costly security risk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let me guess. This is how you create a password: you have the same or similar variation of a password for all the accounts you use at work.&lt;/strong&gt; You might even use the same password for both personal accounts and for work. This poses a serious security risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often do we hear about online scams? We usually comfort ourselves by saying "oh that will never happen to me". The bad news is that we're actually not that special. Ever wonder why websites are asking you to create ever more complex passwords? Because hacking is so common nowadays and passwords are the first line of defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally know of a business owner who's lost $100,000s because their email got hacked. The hackers logged into their email, copied how they sent their invoices and then sent similar invoices with their bank accounts to their clients. They then deleted the sent emails and left no trace. The business owners didn't realise until a month later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The least you can do is to have &lt;strong&gt;unique and complex passwords for all your accounts&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; you should never mix work and personal passwords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On average, you will have approximately &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/firefox/password-dos-and-donts/"&gt;100 accounts&lt;/a&gt; (I have more than 136 at the moment). Imagine, if I figured out the password to one of your accounts, how many accounts do you think I will be able to hack into? 20%? 50%? 90%? Can you imagine if I pretended to be you and asked your clients to pay to my bank account? And an invoice in the Building Industry ain't cheap. We don't like to imagine these hypothetical situations but this is the reality we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Password Managers to the Rescue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to do is to have a password manager so that you can&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;easily&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;use unique passwords for logins.&lt;/strong&gt; I strongly believe that training and the use of password managers should enforced by all companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I needed one which was simple, low cost and was able to work on Android, Windows and Linux which is what I use at home. I have been successfully using Enpass.io for over 2 years now and I can say it is easy to use. It's a little buggy on Android (as of 2020) but I can live with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other ones out there including &lt;a href="https://www.lastpass.com/"&gt;Last Pass&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a href="https://1password.com/sign-up/"&gt;1Password&lt;/a&gt;. You should check out also &lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/lockwise/"&gt;Firefox Lockwise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it Works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Enpass is a great cross platform Password Manager" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/enpass-screenshot-01.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to think of one complex password for the password manager. Here is a screenshot of my list of accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Enpass Screenshot" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/enpass-screenshot-02.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time you need to create an account online, add the details on your password manager as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Enpass Screenshot" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/enpass-screenshot-03.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When coming up with the password, don't be the creative one to think of the password (because your creativity may be lacking). &lt;strong&gt;Let the password manager do the work for you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time you need to login to the site, log into Enpass and copy the password over. That's it. It's faster than trying 5 different passwords, being locked out of your account and then having to reset your password. It's cheaper than being hacked online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/firefox/how-to-create-strong-passwords/"&gt;Read an article about creating strong passwords by Mozilla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go forth, and be safe!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="passwords"></category><category term="security"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Managing Construction Photos</title><link href="https://buildingproductivity.tech/managing-construction-photos.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-20T12:30:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T12:30:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Kim</name></author><id>tag:buildingproductivity.tech,2020-05-20:/managing-construction-photos.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learn how to effectively manage your construction photos.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the construction industry, it is important to have an efficient system in place to take and manage site photos. &lt;strong&gt;They are an important way to document the site before and during construction, as well as to monitor defects.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, I take and use photos all the time. Before, I used to take around 200 photos a week. I use them to share with clients, use these as evidence when raising issues with contractors, and to report on progress with my managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What people usually do is that every time they take photos, they download the photos from their phones onto the computer. They then create a Dropbox folder to share with others if they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However this presents some challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It's hard to sort through annoying thumbnails on Windows (it's not really user friendly)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photos are organised by &lt;strong&gt;folders&lt;/strong&gt; meaning if you want to tag a certain photos, for example "defects", then you need to create and move it into a sub-folder called "defects". And we know what happens to sub-folders within sub-folders - &lt;strong&gt;nobody ends up looking at them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It's hard to sort by date.&lt;/strong&gt; Unless you go into list view which makes looking at photos really hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An easier free way to manage site photos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/google-photo-homepage.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a way I like to manage my work-related photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a separate work smart phone, at least for taking photos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a Google account for work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Google Photos and ensure any photos you take is autmatically uploaded to Google Photo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are managing multiple projects, separate the photos into albums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to collect specific type of photos, create also an album for that "for example, defects"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the project, download all the photos onto the computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first point is quite important, you want to have a separate work phone. &lt;strong&gt;You don't want to be separating personal and work-related photos all the time (this goes for other content too such as messages).&lt;/strong&gt; That way, it's easier to download all the work-related photos onto your computer. You can also confidently show photos on your phone to others without worrying about embarrassing selfies. If you don't have one already, request one from your company. It doesn't need to be the latest flagship phone. It doesn't even need to have a SIM card! Just a camera and wifi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/google-photo-list.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a separate work phone which automatically uploads all photos to the cloud will save you lots of time. And Google Photos is an incredible app that helps you do that. &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/photos/answer/6193313?co=GENIE.Platform%3DiOS&amp;amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;amp;oco=2"&gt;See here&lt;/a&gt; for more detailed instructions from Google on how to set up automatic back up photos. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Things you can do with Google Photo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share albums with your manager and clients to show progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easily manage thousands of photos. You can view the photos as thumbnails and flick through them to find the one you want.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyse the progress of the construction site over the period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have any queries about the site, you can quickly refer back to the photos instead of asking the contractor to take a photo or going there yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can even take videos and watch them on Google Photos (perfect for doing site-walks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can try google searches such as "sign" or "orange" (a bit creepy I know)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="https://buildingproductivity.tech/images/google-photo-search.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, I even collated all the photos that I took and made it into a quick movie showing progress on site. That was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="photos"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry></feed>